Finding Aid for Ralph W. Aigler papers, 1908-1962
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ralph W. Aigler papers 1908-1962, 1920-1940
Aigler, Ralph W. (Ralph William), 1885-
17 linear feet
87406 Aa 2
Aigler was a University of Michigan Law School professor who was heavily involved in university athletics. The collection consists primarily of extensive correspondence and Board in Control of Athletics documentation, but also includes papers written in both his legal and university capacities.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Eileen Aigler estate in April, 2008. Donor no. 10042. Added to a previous acquisition received from the Law School via Paul G. Kauper (donor no. 5383 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Ralph W. Aigler (Feb. 13, 1885-May 24, 1964) was born in Bellevue, Ohio. He received his law degree from Michigan in 1907. Aigler briefly practiced law in Chicago before joining the law faculty at Michigan in 1910 as a full professor and remained at his alma mater until he retired in 1955 Aigler was a nationally renowned expert on real property law and one of the advisors to the American Law Institute in the drafting of the Restatement of the Law of Property. He also served as a visiting professor at other universities, including: Harvard, Columbia, Cornell, Stanford, the University of California and the University of Southern California.
Aigler wrote extensively in the field of law, including two important volumes: "Cases on Property" and "Cases on Bankruptcy." He served as president, treasurer, and secretary of the Association of American Law Schools and various committees on the American Bar Association.
Aigler was heavily involved in athletics at Michigan and held two important posts: the University's faculty representative to the Big Ten Conference from 1917 to 1955, and representative of Michigan's Faculty Board in Control of Athletics from 1917 to 1942 (throughout his tenure he served as chairman several times). Aigler's other contributions included leading Michigan back into the Big Ten Conference, leading the effort to construct Michigan Stadium, Yost Fieldhouse and other facilities, negotiating the Big Ten's exclusive contract with the Rose Bowl starting in 1946, hiring Fritz Crisler as football coach and athletic director, and acting as a spokesman for the University and Big Ten for many years on NCAA rules and eligibility issues. He was inducted into the University of Michigan Athletic Hall of Honor in 1982.
The Aigler collection consists of six series covering his collegiate and professional life: Correspondence, Board in Control of Athletics, Writings, University of Michigan Teaching and Administration, Legal Files, and Biographical. Through correspondence and topical files, the collection documents Aigler's university life and his life-long interest in intercollegiate athletics. The collection has strong potential for research regarding early University of Michigan athletics, and general correspondence to and from Aigler. While there is some material related to Aigler's teaching career, this area is not particularly strong.
Subjects:
Aigler, Ralph W. (Ralph William), 1885-; Big Ten Conference (U.S.); University of Michigan--Sports.; University of Michigan--Board in Control of Athletics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Football.; University of Michigan--Law School.
Contributors:
Crisler, H. O. (Herbert Orin), 1899-1982.; Griffith, John L.; Rickey, Branch, 1881-1965.; Wilson, Kenneth L. (Kenneth Leon), 1896-1979.; Yost, Fielding Harris, 1871-1946.
- Correspondence
  Correspondence (1908-1962; 10 linear feet) contains both letters to Aigler as well as copies of letters he wrote. The early years (prior to 1929) were originally contained in letterboxes, and generally each box contained a single year. After this time period, Aigler began filing his correspondence in vertical files that covered a batch of four to five years that would sometimes overlap with the next batch. Not every person received their own file folder, and thus each letter has a "miscellaneous" file that contains a smattering of letters. The files are organized by last name, though some organizations are filed by their title (i.e. several different authors are filled under the same organization). Most of the correspondence contains a mix of university, athletic, and legal topics, as only a small selection of strictly athletic correspondence had been separated. Several notable people are featured in the correspondence including Branch Rickey, Herbert Crisler, and Fielding Yost.
  - 1908, 1913-1915 (Box 1)
  - 1916-1920, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1921, 6 folders (Box 1)
    (includes separate file for Branch Rickey)
  - 1922, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1923, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1924, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1925, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - 1926 (Box 1)
  - 1927, 10 folders (Box 2)
    (contains separate files for Allan Aigler, John Griffith)
  - 1928, 7 folders (Box 2)
  - 1929-1933
    - Aigler, Allan (Box 3)
    - Admissions Tax (Box 3)
    - American Law Institute (Box 3)
    - Athletics: Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Bates, Dean Henry (Box 3)
    - Bell, Margaret (Box 3)
    - Bennett, Robert (Box 3)
    - Beutel, Frederick (Box 3)
    - Bigelow, Harry (Box 3)
    - Board in Control of Athletics: Administrative-Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Board in Control of Athletics: Budget (Box 3)
    - Bogert, George (Box 3)
    - Booth, D.C. (Box 3)
    - Burke, George (Box 3)
    - Callaghan & Company (Box 3)
    - Griffith, John
      - 1929-1930 (Box 3)
      - 1931 (Box 3)
      - 1932 (Box 3)
    - Hahn, George (Box 4)
    - Harvard Law Review (Box 4)
    - Hibbard, John (Box 4)
    - Kennedy, Charles (Box 4)
    - Law School: Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Long, O.F. (Box 4)
    - Marshall, William (Box 4)
    - May, George (Box 4)
    - Miller, Justin (Box 4)
    - Mitchell, Elmer D. (Box 4)
    - Moenkhaus, W.J. (Box 4)
    - Murfin, James (Box 4)
    - Paige, James (Box 4)
    - Ruthven, Alexander (Box 4)
    - Savage, Howard (Box 4)
    - Smith, Shirley (Box 4)
    - Stone, Ralph (Box 4)
    - Tapping, T. Hawley (Box 5)
    - University of Detroit vs. UM Game (Letters opposing game and commending Board's action) (Box 5)
    - University of Detroit vs. UM Game (Letters in favor of game) (Box 5)
    - Watkins, Herbert (Box 5)
    - West Publishing Co. (Box 5)
    - Williams, C.C. (Box 5)
    - Woodward, Fred (Box 5)
    - Yost, Fielding (Box 5)
  - 1934-1939
    - Aigler, Allan (Box 5)
    - Bell, Margaret (Box 5)
    - Eldridge, Clarence (Box 5)
    - Griffith, John L.
      - March 1933-April 1934 (Box 6)
      - April 1934-January 1, 1936 (Box 6)
      - January 1, 1936-January 1, 1937 (Box 6)
      - January 1, 1937-August 30, 1937 (Box 6)
      - September 1, 1937-July 1939 (Box 6)
    - Hibbard, John (Box 6)
    - Mathews, Ben (Box 6)
    - NCAA (Box 7)
    - Pack, Phillip (Box 7)
    - Paige, James (Box 7)
    - Plant and Equipment Committee (Box 7)
      (University Council)
    - Program and Policy Committee (Box 7)
    - Rickey, Branch (Box 7)
    - Ruthven, Alexander (Box 7)
    - Smith, Shirley (Box 7)
    - University Budgets (Box 7)
    - Ward, Willis (Box 7)
      (Georgia Tech game and racial segregation)
    - West Publishing Co. (Box 7)
    - Wisconsin Case (Box 7)
      (membership in Intercollegiate Conference)
  - 1940-1945
    - Aigler, Allan (Box 8)
    - Aigler, Ralph (Box 8)
    - Big Sag Land & Livestock Co. (Box 8)
    - Burby, William (Box 8)
    - Catlett, J. Bland (Box 8)
    - French, Thomas (Box 8)
    - Griffith, John (Box 8)
    - Metcalf, T.N. (Box 8)
    - Pack, Phillip (Box 8)
    - Richart, Frank (Box 8)
    - Rickey, Branch (Box 8)
    - Rottschaefer, Henry (Box 8)
    - Rundell, Oliver (Box 8)
    - Ruthven, Alexander (Box 8)
    - Smith, Shirley (Box 8)
    - Titles, Act No. 200 1945 (Box 8)
      (real estate interests)
    - Watkins, Herbert (Box 8)
    - Wilson, K.L. (Tug) (Box 8)
    - Works, George (Box 8)
  - 1946-1954
    - Aigler, Allan (Box 9)
    - Bates Contributions (Box 9)
    - Bates Fund (Box 9)
    - Clark, Herbert (Box 9)
    - Connable, Alfred (Box 9)
    - Group Homes Association (Box 9)
      (annexing property to Ann Arbor)
    - Houston, Clarence (Box 9)
    - North Central Association (Box 10)
    - NCAA 4th District (Box 10)
    - Personal 1938-1946 Misc. (Box 10)
    - Reed, William (Box 10)
    - Rottschaefer, Henry (Box 10)
    - West Publishing Co,. 1947 (Box 10)
    - Wilson, K.L (Tug) 1946-1954, 5 folders
    - Miscellaneous prior to 1947: Report: Legal Research Com., etc. (Box 10)
  - 1956 (Box 10)
    (includes Branch Rickey)
  - 1960, 1962 (Box 10)
- Board in Control of Athletics
  Board in Control of Athletics (1920-1955; 4 linear feet) contains related correspondence, meeting records, and papers relating to various committees and endeavors including the building of the stadium and the Rose Bowl debates. This series also includes records of predecessor organizations and files relating to athletics in general.
  - Correspondence
    (arranged alphabetically)
    - 1920-1923, 6 folders (Box 11)
    - 1933-1936
      - Ainsworth, L.W. (Box 11)
      - Bell, Margaret (Box 11)
      - Budgets, University (Box 11)
      - Hibbard, John (Box 11)
      - Iowa State College (Box 11)
    - 1933-1936
      - Mathews, Ben (Box 12)
      - Ruthven, Alexander (Box 12)
    - 1939-1940, 3 folders (Box 12)
      (includes separate file for Herbert Crisler)
  - Eligibility Committee
    - 1945 (Box 13)
    - 1946, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - 1947 (Box 13)
    - 1948 (Box 13)
  - Officials Committee 1923-1926, 5 folders (Box 13)
  - Rose Bowl 1932, 1940, 1946 (Box 13)
    (negotiations relating to Michigan's appearance in the Rose Bowl game, etc.)
  - Stadium Building Committee 1927 (Box 13)
  - University Senate Advisory Committee 1950 (Box 13)
  - Reports
    - 1914-1921 (Box 13)
    - 1922-1928 (Box 13)
    - 1929-1930 (Box 13)
    - 1933-1939 (Box 13)
    - 1940-1948 (Box 13)
    - 1949-1955 (Box 13)
  - Intercollegiate Conference 1929, 1952 (Box 13)
    (memos, reports, etc.)
  - Minutes (and related)
    - 1916-1921 (Box 14)
    - 1922-1924 (Box 14)
    - 1925-1928 (Box 14)
    - 1930 (Box 14)
    - 1931-1933 (Box 14)
    - 1934-1936 (Box 14)
    - 1937-1939 (Box 14)
    - 1940-1942 (Box 14)
    - 1943-1944 (Box 14)
    - 1945 (Box 14)
    - 1946 (Box 14)
    - 1947 (Box 14)
    - 1948 (Box 14)
    - 1949 (Box 14)
    - 1950 (Box 14)
    - 1951 (Box 14)
    - 1952 (Box 14)
    - 1953 (Box 14)
    - 1954 (Box 14)
    - 1955 (Box 14)
- Writings
  The Writings (1 linear feet) series includes manuscripts and published items concerning various legal and athletic issues.
  - Legal, 8 folders (Box 15)
  - Athletics (Box 15)
- University of Michigan Teaching and Administration
  The University of Michigan Teaching and Administration (0.25 linear feet) series contain some of his class notes (used for teaching), exams, and documents his other university administrative capacities.
  - Class Notes, 8 folders (Box 15)
  - Class Notes-Real Property (Box 16)
  - Class Exams (Box 17)
  - Committee on Research Projects (Box 17)
  - University Council (Box 17)
- Legal Files
  The Legal Files (0.25 linear feet) series includes cases he worked on, records of the state bar, and tax records.
  - Legal Cases, 5 folders (Box 17)
  - State Bar of Michigan (Box 17)
  - Tax File (Box 17)
    (concerns the IRS and collecting taxes based upon athletic events)
- Biographical
  The Biographical (0.5 linear feet) series contains many personal papers, a small collection of the papers of his wife, and records about his retirement, obituaries, his memorial fund, and photographs of Aigler and his wife.
  - Papers (Box 17)
    (includes references, NCAA, reunion material, etc.)
  - Politics (Box 17)
    (correspondence regarding the Republican party, foreign policy, etc.)
  - Eileen Aigler (Box 17)
    (correspondence to and from Mrs. Aigler)
  - Social Security Case (Box 17)
  - U of M Aigler Nite 1955, 2 folders (Box 17)
    (honoring retirement, includes seven photographs, letters from Gerald Ford Jr., Crisler, Yost)
  - Clippings (Box 17)
    (mostly newspaper articles concerning Aigler)
  - Memorial Service (Box 17)
  - Memorial Prize (Box 17)
    (recipients and foundation)
  - Photographs of Aigler and wife, 21 photographs (Box 17)